Guide to the Josiah C. Trent papers, 1536-1961 and undated, bulk 1938-1951 RL.01307
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Josiah C. Trent papers
1536-1961 and undated
1938-1951
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Trent, Josiah C. (Josiah Charles), 1914-1948
RL.01307
6.5 Linear Feet 9 boxes; 1 oversize folder approx. 1800 items
U.S. thoracic surgeon, rare book and manuscript collector. The papers consist mostly of correspondence, printed material, photographs, and lecture notes taken during medical training, as well as diplomas and certificates of residency, and notes and drafts for published and unpublished research and articles. The bulk of the material documents Dr. Trent's activities and publications as collector and historian of medical practice, particularly surgery and epidemiology. There are folders of photographic reproductions of medical texts and illustrations dating from the 16th century to the 20th century, whose content is reflected in the earliest dates for the collection. There is also material relating to Dr. Trent's death and the subsequent donation of his rare book and manuscripts collection to the Duke Medical Center Library, along with condolences and other items related to his wife, Mary Duke Biddle Trent. Acquired as part of the History of Medicine Collections at Duke University.
approximately 1800 items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Josiah C. Trent Papers were transferred to the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library from the Medical Center Library in 2011.
Collection Overview
The Josiah C. Trent papers consist mostly of correspondence, photographs, research files, and notes and drafts of published and unpublished research and articles. Many of these materials concern Dr. Trent's activities and publications as a collector and historian of medical practice, particularly surgery and epidemiology. The collection also includes printed materials, photographs, a card file - possibly of his personal library, and lecture notes taken during his medical training, as well as diplomas and certificates of residency. The Writings series reveals his wide interests in surgery, medicine in general, the humanities, and medical history.
There is also material relating to Dr. Trent's death and the subsequent donation of his large rare book, artifact, and manuscript collection to the Duke Medical Center Library. Early dates in the collection refer to the content of reproductions of 16th-19th century medical illustrations rather than their dates of reproduction.
The correspondence, found in the Subject Files folders, dates mostly from the 1940s and 1950s, documenting Dr. Trent's rare book and manuscript collecting, and his involvement with various professional organizations and his association and friendships with prominent figures in various fields: medical history - John Fulton, Henry Sigerist, W. W. Francis; book collecting - Henry Schuman; Duke University - Wilburt Davison, Lenox D. Baker. Some folders contain an index of the contents.
There is also some information concerning Mary Duke Biddle Trent Semans, Dr. Trent's wife, who was instrumental in facilitating the support of the history of medicine collections at Duke.
The collection also contains several hundred photographic prints and negatives reproducing medical texts and illustrations dating from the 16th to 20th centuries. The earliest dates in the collection refer to the content of the images, rather than their reproduction by Dr. Trent, Duke Medical Library staff, and others, in the mid-20th century.
The files were kept in Dr. Trent's medical office and contain relatively few items which pertain to his private life. Items of a more personal nature may be found in the James H. and Mary Duke Biddle Trent Semans Family Papers in the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library.
Acquired as part of the History of Medicine Collections at Duke University.
Collection Arrangement
The Josiah C. Trent Papers are arranged in four series: Medical School Student Papers; Subject Files; Writings; and Photographs.
Related Material
Henry and Ida Schuman papers, circa 1930-1990s (contains correspondence with Dr. Trent), David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
James H. and Mary Duke Biddle Trent Semans Family Papers (record group that forms part of the Semans Family Papers), David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Dr. Josiah Trent Papers (chiefly professional papers as surgeon), Medical Center Archives, Duke University
Trent Manuscripts Collection (over 700 small collections acquired by Dr. Trent; search the term "Forms part of the Trent Manuscripts Collection" in the Duke Libraries catalog), David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Book collecting; Epidemiology -- History; History of Medicine; Medical illustration; Medicine -- Study and teaching; Physicians -- United States -- Correspondence; Surgery -- History; Collectors and collecting -- North Carolina; Negatives (photographs); Photographs; Duke University. Medical Center; Trent, Josiah C. (Josiah Charles), 1914-1948; University of Pennsylvania. School of Medicine; History of Medicine Collections (Duke University); Semans, Mary Duke Biddle Trent; Trent, Josiah C. (Josiah Charles), 1914-1948 -- Library
- Medical training, papers and diplomas, 1930s-1947, 2 boxes; 1 oversize folder
  Scope and Contents note
  Chiefly comprises exam materials, lecture notes, and diplomas and certificates from Dr. Trent's medical training at the University of Pennsylvania, University of Michigan, Ford Hospital (Michigan), and Duke University Medical School. Also contains a few medical licenses and society membership certificates, including one for his wife, Mary Duke Biddle Trent.
  - Examinations, 1937-1938 (Box 1)
  - Lecture notes, circa 1930s-1940s, 5x8 and 4x7 note cards housed in 4 boxes (Box 1)
  - Diplomas and certificates, 1938-1947, 9 items (Box 9)
  - Medical license to practice in North Carolina, 1940 (Oversize-folder 1)
- Subject files, 1852-1869, 1927-1961, bulk 1940s-1950s, 4 boxes
  Scope and Contents
  Contains correspondence, notes, and papers, and a library card file, chiefly relating to Dr. Trent's activities as a collector, and the dedication of the Trent Collection at the Duke University Medical Center Library in 1949. There is also a folder of material on Dr. Trent's death, a folder concerning Mary Duke Biddle Trent, and some financial information. Some folders contain an index and folder description within. Folders are arranged alphabetically by original titles. A library card file is also housed in this series, most likely relating to titles in Dr. Trent's library.
  - 100 Most Influential Medical Books, 1946 (Box 2)
  - Accession--ribbon copy, 1940s (Box 2)
  - Accession--duplicate copy (Box 2)
  - Angina pectoris, surgical treatment of, 1949 (Box 2)
  - Appraisal, 1956, 1961 (Box 2)
  - Army Medical Library News, 1947-1948 (Box 2)
  - Bibliographical notes (Box 2)
  - Bibliography, 1946 (Box 2)
  - Book orders/book dealers, 1944-1948 (Box 2)
  - Bookstore, 1949 and undated (Box 2)
  - Bronchiectasis (Box 2)
  - Bronchoscopies, figures on, 1946-1947 (Box 2)
  - Bronchoscopy, 1934, 1948 (Box 2)
  - Card catalog--inquiries, 1943 (Box 2)
  - Certificate [1948] (Box 2)
  - Death of Josiah C. Trent, 1948-1949, 1956-1958 (Box 2)
  - Dedication of Trent collection, 1949-1957 (Box 2)
  - Dealers' descriptions, A-F (Box 3)
  - Dealers' descriptions, G-M (Box 3)
  - Dealers' descriptions, M-Z, 1951 and undated (Box 3)
  - Duke hospital wards and the eminent men for whom they are named, 1931 (Box 3)
  - Ephemera, 1946-1949 (Box 3)
    Contains photographs, receipts, stamps, license, membership card, and invitation.
  - Esophagus, cancer of, 1929-1941 (Box 3)
  - Films, War Department (Box 3)
  - Hospital of San Hipólito (Box 3)
  - Income tax, 1947 (Box 3)
  - Income tax, 1948 (Box 3)
  - Ivory manikins, 1949 (Box 3)
  - Johnston, Christopher, 1950 (Box 3)
  - Liability policy, 1948 (Box 3)
  - Lists, etc., 1940, 1943 and undated (Box 3)
  - Lithography (Box 3)
  - Memorabilia, Door sign, with "Dr. Trent" (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 3x5 note cards (Box 6)
  - New Gould's Medical Dictionary, 1945 (Box 3)
  - Osler series, 1949-1950 and undated, 2 folders (Box 3-4)
  - Pharmacy jars (Box 4)
  - Reprints, misc., 1936-1948 and undated (Box 4)
  - Selected Readings in Historical Medicine, 1947 (Box 4)
  - Spurzheim portrait, presentation of, 1927 (Box 4)
  - Subscription project, 1949-1950 (Box 4)
  - Trent, Mary--miscellaneous, 1949-1958 and undated (Box 4)
  - Trent collection--clippings, notes, and plans, 1940-1961 (Box 4)
  - The Trent family, 1852-1869, 1947-1959 (Box 4)
  - The U.S. Quarterly Book List, 1947 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence on Walt Whitman, 1947-1948 (Box 4)
  - Library card file (Box 8)
    Cards are contained in one box and probably derive from Dr. Trent's personal library.
- Writings, 1941-1949 and undated, 2 boxes
  Contains notes, drafts, and reprints of articles, publications, and presentations written and given by Dr. Trent. Most are related to historical studies of medical practices, particularly surgery and epidemiology. Unless noted, items are undated. Arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Anesthesia, editorial notes, etc. (Box 4)
  - Benjamin Rush in Edinburgh (Box 4)
  - Benjamin Waterhouse (Box 4)
  - Book reviews, 1945-1948 (Box 4)
  - Chapters in the History of Thoracic Surgery (Box 4)
  - An Evaluation of Extrapleural Pneumonolysis with Lucite Plombage (Box 4)
  - Evolution of the Aseptic Principle in Surgery, 1945-1946 (Box 4)
  - Five Letters of Marcus Aurelius to....John Houghton, 1942 (Box 4)
  - Historical Aspects of Aseptic Surgical Techniques, 1946 (Box 5)
  - History of Yellow Fever, 1948 (Box 5)
  - John Coakley Lettsom and his Literary Friends, 1948 (Box 5)
  - Ligation of the innominate artery, 1946 (Box 5)
  - Medical Supplies in the Confederate Army (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous publications, 1947 and undated (Box 5)
  - Obstetrics and Gynecology in America, 1947 and undated (Box 5)
  - Panel for American Medical Association, 1947-1948 (Box 5)
  - Problems of Civil and Military Emergencies, 1941 (Box 5)
  - Some comments upon the use of barbiturates... (Box 5)
  - Surgical Classics, outline (Box 5)
  - Surgical Therapy of the Patent Ductus Arteriosus (Box 5)
  - Thumbnail Sketches, first series (Box 5)
  - Thumbnail Sketches, correspondence with Dr. Trent, 1945-1949 (Box 5)
  - Thumbnail Sketches, correspondence with Mrs. Trent, 1949 (Box 5)
  - Walt Whitman--a case study (Box 5)
- Photographs, 1536-1946 and undated, 3 boxes
  Contains photographic prints and negatives that are reproductions of medical illustrations and texts dating from the 16th century to the 20th century. These dates refer to the content, and not to Dr. Trent's creation of the prints and negatives, which took place in the 1930s and 1940s. Many of the images are from German sources and some are housed in the Bettmann Archive. The prints and negatives are housed separately in 7.5x5.5 and 9x12 inch envelopes and arranged alphabetically by author or title. Unless otherwise noted, all titles include both negatives and prints.
  - Anatomical figurine. Syphilis. front view (Box 6)
  - Anatomical figurine. Syphilis. right side view (Box 6)
  - Anatomical figurine. Syphilis. left side view (Box 6)
  - Anatomical figurine. Syphilis. rear view (Box 6)
  - Antiseptic operation. From: Cheyne, Antiseptic Surgery (Box 6)
  - Appert, The Art of Preserving.... (1811) (Box 6)
  - Arconville, Essai pour servir à l'histoire de la putrefaction... (1766) (Box 6)
  - Awakening call to the children of New England (Box 6)
  - S. Bard, A compendium of the history and practice of midwifery... (1807) (Box 6)
  - Bergman operating. From: The Bettmann Archive, print only (Box 6)
  - Bigelow, Insensibility during surgical operations... (1846) (Box 6)
  - Billroth operating. From: The Bettmann Archive, print only (Box 6)
  - Boston Medical and Surgical Journal. Nov. 18, 1846 (Box 6)
  - Dewees, A compendious system of midwifery... (1828) (Box 6)
  - Dutertre, Histoire generale des Antilles (1667) (Box 6)
  - Gersdorff, Feldtbuch der Wundt-Artzney (1551), 6 envelopes, prints only (Box 6)
  - Gorgas, A few general directions... (1904) (Box 6)
  - Guenther, Institutions (1536) (Box 6)
  - J. Guiteras, Experimental yellow fever... (1901) (Box 6)
  - Halsted, Ligature and suture material... (1913) (Box 6)
  - Halsted, operating. (1904) From: Mac Cullom's Halsted (Box 6)
  - Harvey, Exercitatio anatomica... (1628) (Box 6)
  - Heister, Laurence. (1731) Pre-antiseptic operation. (Box 6)
  - J. Hester, A hundred and foureteene experiments... (1596) (Box 6)
  - Holmes, The contagiousness of puerperal fever, negatives only (Box 6)
  - J. Hunter, A treatise on the venereal disease (1786) (Box 6)
  - Innominate artery... (fig. 1) (Box 6)
  - Innominate artery... (fig. 2) (Box 6)
  - Innominate artery... (fig. 3) (Box 6)
  - Innominate artery... (fig. 4) (Box 6)
  - Innominate artery... (fig. 5) (Box 6)
  - E. Jenner, An inquiry into the causes and effects of the variolae vaccinae (1798) (Box 6)
  - R. Koch, Gaffky and Loeffler, Versuche über die Verwerthbarkeit heisser Wasserdämpfe... (Box 6)
  - Leeuwenhoek, 4 envelopes, negatives and prints (Box 6)
  - Lister, On a new method of treating compound frature... Lancet, June 1867 (Box 6)
  - Massachusetts General, operating amphitheater. (1888) From: The Bettmann Archive, print only (Box 7)
  - McBurney, operating. From: The Bettmann Archive, print only (Box 7)
  - Meigs, Charles D. portrait, negatives only (Box 7)
  - Morgan, A discourse upon the institution of medical schools... (1765) (Box 7)
  - Valentine Mott, portrait by James Henry Shegogue, 2 envelopes, negatives only (Box 7)
  - V. Mott, portrait by James Henry Shegogue, verso (Box 7)
  - V. Mott, Reflections on securing... (Box 7)
  - V. Mott, Reflections on securing... (fig. 1) (Box 7)
  - V. Mott, Reflections on securing... (fig. 2) (Box 7)
  - Moynihan and Keen, Surgical masks. From: Moynihan, Abdominal operations. 2nd ed.; Keen and DaCosta, Surgery, vol. V, 1920 (Box 7)
  - Neuber, Anleitung zur Technik der antiseptischen Wundbehandlung... (1883) (Box 7)
  - Neuber, Die aseptische Wundbehandlung... (1886) (Box 7)
  - Neuber, Kurz Beschreibung der aseptische Wundbehandlung (1892) (Box 7)
  - J. Nott, On the cause of yellow fever (Box 7)
  - Oliver, A present to be given to teeming women... (1694) (Box 7)
  - Pasteur, Etudes sur le vin (Box 7)
  - Patent ductus. Fig. 1, negatives only (Box 7)
  - Patent ductus. Fig. 2, negatives only (Box 7)
  - Pean, operating. From: The Bettmann Archive, print only (Box 7)
  - Pringle, Appendix, containing experiments upon septic... (Box 7)
  - Pringle, Appendix, containing experiments and observations... (Box 7)
  - Redi, Experimenta (1671), 4 envelopes, prints and negatives (Box 7)
  - W. Reed, et. al. The etiology of yellow fever... (1900) (Box 7)
  - W. Reed, Experimental yellow fever (1901), negatives only (Box 7)
  - B. Rush, An account of the bilious remitting yellow fever (Box 7)
  - B. Rush, Letter to Dr. John Redman Coxe. (1804) From: John Mitchell, On yellow fever in Virginia, 1741 and 1742 (Box 7)
  - Sachs, Ein Gesprech (Box 7)
  - Schimmelbusch, Anleitung zur aseptischen Wundbehandlung (1892) (Box 7)
  - Ein schon geystlich liedt von dem Todt... (Box 7)
  - Semmelweis, Die offenen Briefe... (1899) (Box 7)
  - Severinus, De recondita. (1632) (Box 7)
  - Severinus, Letter to John Houghton (1640), obverse (Box 7)
  - Severinus, Letter to John Houghton (1640), reverse (Box 7)
  - Severinus, portrait (Box 7)
  - Severinus, Zootomia Democritæa, 4 envelopes, negatives and prints (Box 7)
  - Smythe, Letter (1773) (Box 7)
  - Sternberg, Report on the etiology and prevention of yellow fever (1890), negatives only (Box 7)
  - J. Sterns. Letter to Mr. S. Akerly (1807), negatives only (Box 7)
  - Struck, Mittheilungen aus dem kaiserlichen Gesundheitsamte (1881) (Box 7)
  - Theodoric of Cervia (Box 7)
  - Unidentified portrait, negatives only (Box 7)
  - Vesalius, prints only (Box 7)
  - Watts, Mott, and Stevens. The Medical and Surgical Register (1818) (Box 7)
  - Oversize photographs (7.5x10.5 envelopes)
    - Finlay, El mosquito hipoteticamente considerado como agente..., prints only (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Institutionum anatomicarum secundum Galeni..., prints only (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Ein schon geystlich liedt von dem Todt..., print only (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Vesalius, print only (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Oversize photographs (9x12 envelopes)
    - Institutionum anatomicarum secundum Galeni..., print, mounted (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Severinus, Letter to John Houghton (1640), prints, mounted (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Severinus, portrait, print, mounted (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Severinus, Zootomia Democritæa... (1645), print, mounted (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Dr. T. Rush Spencer and staff (1862), print only (Box 1, Folder 2)